this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
SC radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
door / software welcome to another
episode of SC radio my name is Johannes
and today I want to talk about
continuous delivery and with me is Jess
humble welcome to the show thanks very
much thanks for having me on
so who's just humble just humble is
currently vice president at chef and he
has 14 years of experience in IT he
worked among other things as a developer
this is admin and consultants and the
interesting thing is he apparently
started programming with 11 years and
was fascinated by sit by his then
spectrum as ZX Spectrum but he went on
to have a BA in physics and philosophy
at Oxford most people will probably know
him about the or one of the authors of
continuous delivery and also of his
upcoming book in enterprise that's right
thank you so today's show will be mainly
about the continuous delivery book and
what happened since he published it in
so maybe Jess can you start was giving
us a 10,000 feet overview over
continuous delivery sure so continuous
delivery came from the experiences that
me and a bunch of other people working
at ThoughtWorks had where we were
working on these pretty large complex
projects and release would always be a
really painful process and it was
somewhere where thought Wes wasn't
really involved we were tend to be doing
the development work and then the
software would have to go somewhere else
to be kind of release to production and
and that was always a very
and difficult and painful process and I
think obviously thought is one of the
people who pioneered and helps
popularize continuous integration so we
were pretty good at actually integrating
the code regularly and running automated
tests regularly but what we would find
is that wasn't enough to get it
production ready and the particular
project that I worked on that really
woke me up to these problems was a
broadband provisioning system that we
wrote for an ISP where we were all
working on Windows laptops but the
software was going to be deployed to a
Solaris cluster and the first time we
were able to get our hands on a
production like environment was over six
months into the project and it took us
to three weeks to get it deployed and
when we got it deployed we found all
these architectural problems that were
caused by people making bad assumptions
so people would do things like hashing
dates to the file system which works
fine on a Windows laptop doesn't work in
a cluster because there's all the
servers have a different file system so
we found all these problems and it was
really expensive to fix them and there
was some automated scripts to help build
and deploy a system that were written in
ants but the operations team they were
not interested in using and so you know
we asked them what what do you want to
use to deploy to production they said
well we want to use bash and so I ended
up writing the system in in bash to do
the deployment called Conan the deployer
after the kind of cult American film
featuring Arnold Schwarzenegger and you
know there was a team of a of us in the
end who were building and evolving this
software so that we could deploy
regularly to test environments and get
tests feedback and appoint production
and so all of these techniques went into
the continuous delivery book and I think
kind of what made it successful was the
people working in large-scale web
systems were simultaneously using very
similar techniques so while we were
writing the book the mvu people that was
the company that Eric Ries co-founded
Tim Fitz wrote this blog post about
continuous deployment an MBE that caused
a huge storm because they were deploying
to production multiple times a day and
then obviously journalist poor and Paul
Hammond it's well at the time it was
Flickr did their talk at velocity 2009
about deploying ten times a day then the
whole cloud thing was coming up DevOps
was coming out so I think there was a
confluence of people who all at the same
time came upon the same set of
techniques that went into continuous
delivery but fundamentally all the
continuous delivery is is about changing
the economics of the software delivery
process to make it economic to work in
small batches so the reason we have
these very waterfall processes still
even in agile shops is because there is
because the process of going from their
starting up a project to getting
approval to budget sign-off to
requirements to then development and
then integration and release is still a
pretty expensive process so it's it's
not economic to work in small
incremental steps and what continuous
really does is continuous delivery
really does is changes the economics of
that so that you can work in small
batches and take small changes through
yeah so and you achieve that by saying
it in one sense automating everything
from the start to the end from the
check-in to the deployment so that's one
piece of it having an automated process
for going from check-in to release is
one part of it I think architecture is
another part configuration management is
another part making sure that everything
that you need to reproduce your
production environment is in version
control and then also there's a bunch of
practices like continuous integration
that also have to be followed in order
to be able to do it effectively yeah
before we dive deeper into the topic of
configuration management and continuous
delivery err continuous integration can
you give me an example of a successful
project you did with continuous delivery
to make it more
real for people yeah so the ISP is one
example and the other thing and people
have seen the continuous delivery is for
web software but that's really not the
case so I was product manager for an
open-source tool called go Cassini's
delivery tool and that was packaged
software but we implemented continuous
delivery there in the sense that every
change words result in packages being
created and then we would run automated
tests but we would also create
installers so we would create solaris
installers windows installers MacOS
installers various flavors of Linux
installer and I think we do the Solaris
ones anymore we do the other ones still
and we would actually do upgrade testing
so we'd have a deployment pipeline that
created the installers and then we would
have copies of some of our customers
brush environments that have been data
scrubbed and when practice and they're
taking that environment and running the
installer to upgrade it and making sure
that the upgrade process worked using
the installers so that was great for
packaged software and it was very
effective because it meant the release
was simply uploading the installers to
the FTP site my people could download
them the other example that I find
really interesting that I wasn't
personally involved in although I do
know the guy he was who wrote the book
it's a book called I think it's called a
large-scale agile development by a guy
who Gary groover and it's about HP
LaserJet firmware and how they
implemented continuous delivery for HP
LaserJet firmware now people don't
upgrade their firmware ten times a day
normally that's not something there you
see very often and nevertheless they
implemented continuous delivery in the
sense of having a very comprehensive
suite of automated tests everyone
checking into trunk and it was a very
large team it was 400 people distributed
across three countries working on what
became a ten million line codebase and
they were able to push in about a
hundred changes a day about a hundred
thousand lines of codes changing every
day and they got about 10 good builds
out of trunk every day and then ran this
extensive battery of automated tests and
they would get complete regression
feedback within one day on the quality
of that and they made sure that they
fixed any bugs they found straightaway
so that the software was always in a
releasable state and that made a huge
difference to the economics of their
process they were able to get an eight
times productivity increase in terms of
the amount of time the team was spending
on building features and fixing bugs
rather than you know activities like
manual testing or merging code between
branches because they weren't using the
trunk based development presence before
and all these kind of non-value add
activities a lot of that just got taken
away and it meant because they had no
more stabilization and integration phase
they could introduce new features very
late in the development process after
what would have been feature freeze
before mmm and that changed their
relationship with the marketing in sales
people as well hmm
so um so when I hear you talking it
sounds a lot like continuous delivery
brings a lot of advantages for business
but when I look at is the developer is
there any thing which is for me except
that the business obviously pays me
right which is a great question I think
there's actually a lot not to like for
developers in in continuous delivery one
of my favorite articles about continuous
delivery is oh I mean it's not actually
primarily about continuous delivery but
it it touches on it is a post that Steve
Yeager wrote so Steve Yeager if you just
type Stevie a gaze platform ran into
Google and some why we usually link them
in the shona great way that's perfect
says ye GG II he wrote this big rant
about how Google doesn't understand
platforms in the way that Amazon does
one of the things he talks about is how
for developers working at Amazon it was
really painful because you had to do all
these things like making sure the code
worked in production and understanding
monitoring and stuff like that that were
not part of what most engineers
understand to be their job and say we're
doing all this other stuff that
prevented you from just hacking out code
and that was pretty annoying but this
comes from Verner Vogel's who is CTO of
Amazon he has the saying you build it
you run it
so the people who are responsible for
building the software also have to run
it in production and that means you have
to understand how to do that and that's
a big cultural change for developers but
it's also a really important feedback
loop because it means developers have to
understand what it means to have
production ready code not just they've
complete codes and that's super
important for developers to actually
understand that because then you have to
really think about these concerns like
scalability and availability and writing
blog messages that are useful and not
just pages and pages of null pointer
exceptions
and things like archiving data these are
all concerns that developers have to
build the software with these things in
mind and unless you have that feedback
loop of understanding what its lights
operate in the software you build it's
very difficult for developers to learn
that stuff so that can actually be
really annoying for developers the other
thing that's a big cultural change with
developers is working out how to take
big features and break them into small
incremental steps that are deployable
that can go into trunk and be deployed
even though they're not finished in
rather than working on feature branches
and that's the big cultural change for
developers because it slows them down in
a sense in the you know going from A to
B in small incremental steps might take
longer than it would if you were on a
feature branch but I think what's really
nice about it to come back to your
question is that it means that as a
developer you can take something take an
idea put something into production and
immediately see the impact of that and
you get this really tight feedback loop
of doing something and then maybe even
the same day certainly within a week
actually being able to see people
actually interacting with that code
rather than the traditional model where
you have to wait weeks or even months to
see you know I've worked on projects
where the software went live after I'd
already left the project and was working
on something else so I never got to see
people actually using the software I'd
bill and that's pretty miserable as a
developer it's nice to actually be able
to push stuff out and have see people
use it and get feedback on it that I
think that's actually really really
great as your approach to developing
software changed since you are like you
would say nearer to the customer since
you're nearer to your users
it's funny because I never really
experienced the bad way of doing it I
mean my first job after I graduated from
college was working at a start-up in
London where you know I like to drag
that we were doing continuous delivery
canoes deployment even because we were
FTP files directly from our workstations
into production in in back in 2000 we
weren't even using version control it
was just there was me and the guy he was
the CTO and we just F tp'ed stuff so you
know it's like I certainly wouldn't
recommend now but it was fun at the time
and then I went from there to thought
works where we work on these big
projects where you know we had these
problems we talked about so you know my
first experience was working in a
continuous deployment environment so
yeah I definitely felt the pain of what
it was like to not be doing that and
just be hacking out code for weeks and
weeks that never saw any releases and
obviously that was much worse but I
think if you've never experienced it it
can be hard to see what the benefits are
and this is just a problem with
developers in general I mean I never
used to do any kind of TDD before I
joined footworks
and then I went to work on a team where
everyone did and I was brainwashed but
you know I have Stockholm Syndrome I
love doing it that way I would never do
it any other way now so I think you know
I've had that experience of going from A
to B and I remember when the XP book
first came out and I read it and I was
like oh this will never work
and then I went to work I thought works
with people who did TDD and it was just
the way they developed software and I
was like you know I had an epiphany oh
my god not only does this work but it's
so much more fun as a way developing
software than than doing it any other
way so I think it's it's so difficult to
kind of rationalize and try and convince
people using rational arguments the only
way to do it is to try it for yourself
and work with people who love doing it
that way and and even then it will take
you months to work I have to do it
that's actually a good point
so assuming I'm in a waterfall shop
I have a large multi-million website
whatever how do I start with continuous
delivery yeah that's a great question
and it is really hard because there's so
much that needs to change it's not just
the development process it's how you
think about project management it's how
you think about even the budgeting
process and risk management as well all
that stuff has to change and I think the
only way is to do it slowly and
incrementally as with product
development is there some but the
particular thing where you think you
would start with so I'll give you an
example from Amazon Amazon actually
Ryoga tected from a monolithic
architecture to a service-oriented
architecture and it took them four years
to do it and they used a pattern that
Martin Fowler and other people have
blogged about extensively called the
strangler application pattern because
often the architecture is the biggest
obstacle or one of the biggest obstacles
practically achieving continuous
delivery if you have to deploy
everything in the world you know all
your system is in a big bang way it's
very difficult to see some of the
benefits so what Amazon did was they
reacted to a service-oriented
architecture but they did it
incrementally so they would peel off a
particular service and re-implement that
and over time they would gradually peel
more and more services out and it's like
I mean the metaphor for the strangle
application is in tropical rainforests
you have these trees and then there's a
fig vine that grows up around the tree
and gradually strangles the tree and all
that's left is the fig vine and there
the tree that it's grown around dies and
that's what we're trying to do
architectural pull out all these little
services and then gradually strangle the
monolithic out and that was I think what
Amazon did which was really clever was
combined that with an organizational
change which was you Bill de run it the
idea that they had a team that was
responsible for each service throughout
its entire lifecycle and they had this
idea of two pizza teams that there was
no team that would be bigger and you
could feed with two pizzas so no more
than about 10 people and that
responsible for that service over its
lifecycle and so that imposes a limit on
the size of the service which I think
you know we're seeing an upsurge of
interest in micro services which is kind
of the architecture that Amazon
pioneered although there's some argument
about what defines the micro of the
micro service obviously and I think what
was clever about Amazon is that they
leveraged Conway's law so Conway's law
says that the architecture of a system
reflects its communication structure or
is determined by the communication
structure of the organization that
builds that architecture and so by
saying ok we're going to have this
service-oriented architecture and we're
gonna have one team per service that was
that was a really smart move and again
stevia goes platformer and talks about
this they actually hired an ex-army
Ranger whose job it was to go to all of
the teams and make sure they weren't
talking to other teams databases so this
guy Rick Dalzell would go round and if
he found you talking to another team's
database not through their service layer
he would shout at you a lot and you know
if you carry on doing it he would try
and have you fired
coming back to Conway's law so what
you're effectively saying is by putting
the people responsible for operations in
the development team together was the
business teams you create the need for
continuous delivery because people are
sitting together working together have
the same boss and so they start dealing
with deployment together which leads to
continuous delivery that's right and and
the architecture as well because the
architecture is a key part but yeah
you've aligned you crazy
cross-functional teams which means that
again I mean coming back to the idea of
making it economic to work in small
batches
you've got the architectural piece
and you've also got the team structure
where developers can push changes
themselves out to production they don't
need to go through this a very onerous
change centralized change management
process to get things out they can just
you know push things out within their
team so yeah it's it's the
organizational part and the
architectural part and they're aligned
changing a bit the tropic and going a
little bit deeper into the process of
continuous delivery in your book you say
a release should not be scary why US
releases scary these days I think
releases are scary for a few reasons
firstly in a lot of organizations which
haven't architected their software for
continuous delivery it's just a very
onerous process getting releases out so
I'm sure people listening to this show
there'll be a number of you we were he'd
push out releases outside of business
hours so evenings weekends and it's a
multi hour process and then I think
there's two key metrics the number of
hours you spend outside of normal
business I was pushing out the release
and then also things like how many
emergency fixes you have per a fter
words though those are kind of two
useful metrics but also the other thing
that scary is well this when all these
new features actually deliver value to
the business and to our customers so
finding out whether something you've
built is actually valuable again the
data shows Ronnie Co Harvey has a great
paper he's the guy who developed
Amazon's a/b testing framework and then
went on to Microsoft and built their
experimentation platform for Bing he has
all this data from a/b test that shows
that two-thirds of the features that
thought the P the people thought would
be really good ideas deliver zero or
negative value to customers so if you
generalize that data
you know two-thirds of the features we
build deliver zero or even negative
value to customers they make things
worse that should be scary and you know
we should be we should be finding out a
lot of companies don't even gather that
data and if you're working in 3-month
releases how do you work out which of
those features actually use
responsible for either the increase or
decrease in the business metrics you
care about you know revenue per user or
whatever because so many other things
change and that right so much has
changed how do you trace back to work
out which of the things he did was
actually valuable you know Josh karaoke
talks about yeah he wants to be able to
assign a dollar value to every line of
code I which are the lines of code that
are actually producing value for me you
know we can't do that but we can at
least if we're working in small batches
and doing a/b tests we should at least
be able to see which these features is
actually delivering revenue um and why
what makes automating releases and doing
it more frequently releases less scary
which is a great question because it
seems counterintuitive right it seems if
you deploy if deploying is painful and
you doing more frequently it seems like
that's crazy and I think it's like more
pain you right it sounds like more pain
but the thing is you were deploying less
stuff so there's a few things firstly
you practice it more and that means you
get good at it
and it kind of forces you to simplify I
mean the thing that the thing that has
to go with automation is simplification
if you take a painful manual process and
you just automate it what you end up
with is a painful flaky automated
process and it's not actually an
improvement and you need to reactivate
your software to make it so that it's
easy to deploy which is the architecture
piece so there's a simplification that
goes along with the automation and so
that reduces some of the risk doing it
more frequently reduces through some of
the risks as you get to practice it and
then also just because there's less
stuff that's changing between releases
we're not saying take three months worth
of stuff and release that ten times a
day we're saying take a tenth of a day's
worth of stuff and release that ten
times a day which might be just a single
line of code or a single configuration
change and so when the amount of stuff
you're releasing is much lower if there
something goes wrong it's much easier to
find the problem and it's much easier to
fix the problem yeah
um I would like to mention the word fix
forward in this in this instance can you
elaborate on that yes a this is
something we see in high-performance
organizations that have done this for a
long time is that they never roll back
they always roll forward if they find a
problem so one of the techniques that we
talked about in the book is Bluegreen
deployments Bluegreen deployments is
this idea that you basically have two
copies of production and one of them is
live and one of them is not live you
might call it staging and what you do is
you deploy to the staging environment
and then you switch the load balancer or
Rooter or DNS to point to the staging
environment and then station becomes
live and what was live becomes staging
and this is something that I mean
Netflix have talked about they call it
red-black deployments but what they
basically do is they deploy to staging
and then they slowly migrate users from
one to the other and I think actually
what they do now is Europe is their
staging environment basically but
because of that what they can do is if
they find a problem during deployment
they just switch the users back to the
old life and so as a result of that they
never need to rollback they just
redeploy a new bill to the staging
environment and then gradually migrate
users to that and then rollback is
actually just pushing the users to go
back to the the main live environment so
yeah I mean organizations that are
really good at this just just keep
rolling forward you know I actually
asked Diane marsh she runs
engineering tooling for Netflix do you
even keep around your builds and she's
like well yeah they're somewhere but
we've never rolled back so he never
needs to redeploy or builds so does that
mean that when I deploy more frequently
I'm also faster to fix it
bad things escape live yeah because
again it's much quicker to change a
route a setting to do a you know quote
rollback on quote than it is to try and
redeploy a previous build I mean and
also this is not our practice we test
very often the reason
production deployments are different
from deploying to staging for example or
testing environments is that you've got
all this production data to worry about
so often rollback especially if it
involves data changes that's actually a
pretty high-risk process and not one
that people test very often so rollback
can actually be very very risky um you
mentioned a B tests a couple of time can
you explain shortly what an it a B tests
this and why it is important for
continuous delivery sure so a B testing
actually came from male marketing so
people who had spam your real physical
mailbox with post advertisers they would
send different versions of their
promotions to different people and see
which version of the advertising copy
produced the biggest response rate and
so how do you do this in software well
you have two different versions of a
page and you show some users one version
you so show some users another version
and you have to track this throughout
their entire session so you create
what's called a cohort which is a group
of users that come to the site are
roughly the same time and you track
their progress through the site
including whether they saw version a or
version B of a particular page and then
you see at the end of their journey
which has actually produced the desired
business behavior which might be
something like Amazon whether you
checkout and the ends or write how much
you end up buying at the end you find
the primary outcome right there's this
what call it's what's called the overall
evaluation criteria for the experiment
and you see over time and you have to
collect quite a lot of data to get
statistically significant information so
you collect that data over time with
your cohorts and find out which version
of the page produces the right outcome
and if you look at companies like Amazon
being Etsy they're running a number of
different a/b testing production you
know tens or even in some cases up to a
hundred a/b tests but they control very
carefully which cohorts get to see which
combination of variations because
obviously you don't want the test
interacting with each other here yeah
multivariate tests are a pain right
okay let's switch our focus a little bit
from why we are doing it - how does our
organization how does our culture need
to change in the book you say
continuously livery has its origins in
lean can you explain what you mean
mother yeah I think this is only
something I realized as we were right in
the burqa you know I read Mary
poppendieck and Tom papa Dix book lean
software development back in I think
2004 or 2005 it came out and that that
was a big revelation and then as I was
writing a continuous delivery but with
Dave we did a you know we were still
reading a bunch of other stuff on lean
and it kind of came to me that a lot of
these ideas had their roots in lean
philosophy so one idea I like to talk
about that comes from lean philosophy is
judoka which is a concept that was
actually invented in 1924 by the Toyota
family I think it was Sakichi Toyoda
when they were working on looms so
Toyota used to build looms for weaving
before they moved to cars and their
breakthrough product was the Toyota
automatic loom type G which had this
innovative feature that it could detect
if there was a problem with the weaving
process so if a thread broke or if a
spool ran out of thread it would also
massively stop and notify the user like
continuous integration these days
exactly and it's the same practice right
which is that something goes wrong you
find out about it straightaway and in
the case of the Loom what this meant was
instead of having to have an operator
for every loom they could have a whole
roomful of looms and just one Operator
because the machine would tell you when
there was something wrong and with
continuous integration which is exactly
as you point out an analogous process
again instead of having testers manually
inspects the software you have automated
tests in place and you find out
straightaway if there's a serious
regression and then you can stop and fix
the problem straight away and that makes
the software process much more efficient
it's this idea of building quality in
this idea the Deming talked about in the
social quality movement they were going
to build quality into the software so
many of these ideas including that one
come from lean philosophy mmm-hmm
[Music]
another thing you mention in the book
about the culture is this ideal to
optimize cycle time what is the cycle
here and that's a great question I mean
again taking the metaphor of lean the
the cycle time is very easy to define
because it's I mean you can actually
physically watch the movement of
inventory through the factory you can
see the cars going on the production
line or whatever but software
development it's much harder to be
tangible about the inventory which is we
don't have so many cycles we have
iterations we have a right so it's like
are they features are we measuring is a
features the inventory and if so how do
we measure the movement of features
what's the starting point of a feature
is it a point when you have first have
the idea is at the point when you move
it where you type the idea into a
tracking system will write it on a card
or is it the time at which you put it
into your prioritized backlog but I mean
how where do we even start the clock
right so I think what I would where will
you start the clock and where would you
stop it well I think for continuous
delivery in a kind of very specific
sense the one place where is very
concrete is where you start having
check-ins to version control so
I think you know it's not the full cycle
and we need to be a bit careful about it
to not exclude the kind of front end of
ideation and analysis but I need check
encodings production
oh sorry when you check code into
version control and you measure how long
it takes from being checked into version
control to getting into production that
is very concrete and definable and and
the the production line metaphor that we
use in the continuous delivery book is
uses the metaphor that the production
line in software is the process of
taking a change in version control and
then running tests against dirt hang it
into packages and ultimately deploying
it to production or releasing packages
to users or released to manufacturing in
the case of firmware or something like
that yeah and this is what you call the
deployment point
yeah the deployment pipeline and the
deployment pipeline is it just an
automatic process can I just have a vest
script which does the deployment
pipeline yeah you you can although I
think there will typically be manual
validations so in most cases we wouldn't
be happy taking software that's passed
the automated test and deploying it
straight to production you'll want to do
some kind of user testing maybe a/b
testing and this there's some complexity
with dart launching and so forth what is
Derrick launching Doug launching so this
is a term that was invented I think by
Facebook and and is used by Ed see where
you take code and you push it into
production but those code paths are not
executed but you toggle the futures yeah
you toggle the features or you put them
behind an API and nothing in the UI
actually is connected to the API yeah so
that would be another way to do it but
yeah for example an Etsy most of the
code changes go out doc and then they're
kind of wired up subsequently and that
that's a completely independent
operation and that can be done but I
mean Facebook have a piece of software
called gatekeeper which controls for
each feature exactly who can see it so
you can take a particular feature and
show it to a particular demographic or
roll it out to 1% of users for the
purposes of either
be testing or for even final rollout or
even for managing loads so if you have
unusually high load on your system you
can turn off some of the expensive
features that's something a lot of
organizations practice so can a feature
toggling dark launching is is useful for
a number of different purposes in fact I
heard at some point that this means you
separate release from deployment yeah
that's that's something that I like to
talk about a lot but I really realized
after the book came out it might have
been you but I really don't know where
know it yeah I know I mean I certainly
write about it I don't know if I was the
person who invented the concept probably
not but the idea is deployment is taking
a build and putting it into an
environment release is making a feature
available to users and those are two
completely independent operations often
we couple them we achieve release
through deployment but that's actually
very risky a much less risky way to do
it is to launch all the features dark
which is deployment and you're doing
that all the time but then release in
the sense of making features available
to users is a much more gradual
incremental process that happens
completely out of band is totally
orthogonal to the deployment process and
it's done by by the business by doing
a/b tests by gradually ramping up
functionality and switching them often
they're broken
yes switching off of his broken orifice
like there's high load or something like
that
one large part we haven't talked about
yet in continuous delivery is the
operations part so how is continuous the
delivery linked to what we call dev ops
and the dev ops culture yeah that's a an
interesting question because the DevOps
movement was
basically becoming widespread around the
time we were writing the book to the
extent that we actually got the word
DevOps into the book I remember and I'm
reading a bunch of stuff about Davos and
and talking to a bunch of people about
it and getting very excited about sin
and related Judy named the book the
devops Bible or something like that I
don't know I'm quite happy with her with
the title of the book actually I think I
worked out quite well but I think DevOps
is definitely part of it I think
DevOps came from the webapps movement
and actually the book that came out
before continuous delivery was a web
operations which wonder what does web of
operations and why is different than
DevOps so where operations was I mean
it's this book that was edited by Jesse
Robbins who is head of ops master of
disaster er Amazon and John all spore
who at the time was head of opposite
Flickr is actually not nearly as
well-known as it should be as a whole
collection of essays by people including
Andrew Schafer and Eric Ries and a bunch
of other people who were very well-known
today but at the time weren't so well
known about how to build web scale
systems like Facebook and Amazon and so
forth so where operations was people
working at how to build large-scale
websites and so that's when the DevOps
movement came from originally where's
all that other people other systems
except where also can do web pops Easter
stuff I mean they didn't really care
about those things they didn't and they
didn't care about building user
installed software package software
firmware anything like that they were
purely focused on high-volume websites
and and Devitt was really came out of
that and they weren't really focused on
any other domains at all whereas
continuous livery came from a slightly
different backgrounds and I think what
we found is there
a lot of the ideas in terms of the lean
philosophy the practices and the culture
ended up being the same and that was
really what was very cool about it and I
think led to it becoming such a paradigm
shift is that we found that the same
ideas around culture and practices were
the same they across different domains
from building highly scalable web sites
to building firmware to building
packaged software but actually you could
apply the same ideas across these
different domains and have these really
good outcomes because fundamentally it
was about building Brazilian
organizations and about cultural shift
as much as it was about the particular
practices you use and you know one of
the things that annoys me is you're
going to places and they'll say well
that sounds great but that can't
possibly work here you know we're not
Facebook
we're financial services and the problem
is some truth truth well that there
isn't there isn't I think that the
problem is I have seen these practices
work in the context of financial
services now I worked in an investment
bank for footworks
in 2005 where we implemented a bunch of
the practices in the continuous delivery
book and they were very effective and
they made it they made a big difference
so I know that it's not I mean I was
working on systems that would price
swaps millions of hundreds of millions
of dollars worth of assets so so that
there was significant amounts of money
at risk here and we were using these
practices because they actually make it
safer this is the thing people say well
it can't work here really improving the
quality of your software and finding
bugs faster won't work here gosh you
know and this is what I find kind of
ironic is that you go to these places
they say oh that can't work here because
we're risk-averse these practices are
designed to make it lower risk and
higher quality so what you're saying is
we don't want to do that we want to
continue doing all these kind of cowboy
practices but actually make things worse
I was involved in the state of DevOps
report this year 2014 state of DevOps
report
and there'll be a link in the show notes
for this one of the things we looked at
is we measured IT performance in terms
of throughput which was release
frequency and change lead time in the
way we defined it earlier and also
stability in terms of time to restore
service when there's a outage or a
degradation and change fail rate the
percentage of changes that fail after
you deploy where you have to put a
hotfix or rollback and what we found is
the kind of heavy weight change
management processes that a lot of these
organizations use like having change
advisory boards and so forth
obviously they decrease three Trouper
they make it slower to get changes out
but the really surprising result is they
do nothing to improve stability so we
compared people using those kinds of
heavyweight change processes to
organizations that use peer review where
developers check each other's work
either through a lightweight change
approval process or through just pair
programming and we found obviously that
creates much higher throughput I was
expecting to see that reduced ability
and the surprising result was that it
did not at all it's it's as good at
creating stable systems as heavyweight
change management processes so this idea
oh it can't possibly work here it's just
wrong and psychologically I understand
why people think that because they think
oh we're not hammers and we have
different problems but they forget in
your amazon has sarbanes-oxley they're a
listed company they have PCI DSS they
have they process probably the largest
number of credit card transactions and
ecome company in the world or you know
it's certainly that order of magnitude
so their subjects these regulations I
think the mistake people make
in these large organizations is they
take a one-size-fits-all approach they
say these are regulations and we're
going to apply them to all the different
systems and high-performance companies
don't do that they say well actually not
all of our software is involved with
credit card processing only this
particular service is doing the credit
card processing so what we'll do is
we'll limit the scope of the regulation
to a small surface area as possible and
architect so that the software that does
that is as small as possible
and so you take a very nuanced approach
to risk management where you say well
actually where is the locus of these
risks and how can we apply risk
management in a way where it doesn't
impact the whole system and where this
system where we don't care about PCI DSS
developers can push changes to
production but this system where we
actually do have credit card data where
we're going to take a more nuanced
approach but then also Etsy has PCI DSS
PCI DSS specifies segregation of duties
in other words that the person who
approves the change can't be the same
person he writes the code no where does
it specify that those people can't sit
next to each other so for example at
Etsy the people working on the PCI DSS
to DSS environment they all sit in a
room together
the ops people the developers the
testers they all sit in a room together
and they talk to each other all the time
and implement influence in these
regulations in a way that follows the
spirit and the letter of the law but not
in a very kind of heavyweight segregated
ways is also important yeah um I read
you a comment here a quote from the book
which is everybody is responsible for
the delivery process is that a summary
of DevOps yeah it's it's a pretty good
summary everyone is responsible for the
delivery process that's right I think
everyone is responsible for everything
if you look at high-performing
organizations developers consider
themselves responsible for business
results there's not this thing where you
know this is my job this is my role and
anything outside of that is not my
problem is someone else's problem in
high-performing organizations people
don't think like that they think that
everything is is my problem and and you
know it's not this is my bit and if if
this thing gets screwed up over here
that's their fault you don't have this
mentality and we create cultures where
people do feel that they're responsible
for everything the question we asked in
the state of DevOps report is when dev
and ops interact is the outcome usually
win-win and that was the key question
that brought out the DevOps thing was
was it win-win when these things
interact but if you look at the kind of
cultural substrate that creates those
good outcomes it's that you know
developers consider operations part of
their responsibility you know is if
something goes wrong in ops you know
it's not oh well it must be ops fault
they're so dumb and likewise you know if
they operate if deployment process fails
it's not like oh the stupid developers
you actually work together and we
organize our but our companies in a way
where people are as closely is possibly
connected to customers so developers are
connected to customers everyone's
connected to customers which is another
idea that comes back to lean how
important is that the ops people are the
people focus on ops and the people
focused on dev sitting next to each
other I actually think is pretty
important you know I want to be careful
about this there's there's a great quote
a really good book that I love about
lean is a by a guy called Mike rather
and it's called Toyota kata and Toyota
kata is a boat that describes the
management philosophy of continuous
improvement though the Toyota follow and
it's really key to implementing many of
these ideas one of the thing he says is
that it's not the form of the
organization that's decisive it's the
behavior of the people and so a lot of
companies undertake reorg
in order to achieve some of these things
we talked about and reorg SAR neither
necessary nor sufficient for achieving
these outcomes what has to change is
people's behavior and how do we change
people's behavior if not sitting like
them next to each other that's a great
question and I think that's absolutely
I mean sitting next to each other is one
way to do that and certainly if you look
at companies like Google and Facebook
their own certainly Google I know they
have a service that they have these
services and they're not cheap eats of
teams I mean they're not ten people but
some of these services there's maybe you
know tens of people involved together
and they make sure they all sit on the
same floor so you might have a desk of a
bunch of engineer sitting together and
this desk with a bunch of ops people and
they're not on the same table but they
are in the same floor space but Google
and Amazon I have all the polite minded
forward-thinking developers and not the
old guy who doesn't want to change right
so so there is an element of that and I
think I mean my favorite story about
culture change
is actually a case study from Toyota
against oh sorry to bang the Toyota drum
but it's just a source because they've
been doing it so long there's so many
great stories so there's a podcast on
this American Life which is actually one
of my favorite podcasts and it talks
about new me new United motor
manufacturing company which was a joint
venture that was set up between Toyota
and General Motors in America so I live
in California and actually the new me
plant was in Fremont and it was on the
same site as a previous GM part that was
called Fremont assembly so Fremont
assembly was shut down because the
quality of the cars they were producing
was really horrible and the people on
the production line were really
miserable they hated their jobs and it
got to the stage where they would do
things like sabotage the cars by putting
empty coke bottles in the doors so that
they rattled around when people shut
them and they were really that they
would do things like drinking on the job
and so the plan got closed down because
it was just so cost inefficient and poor
quality and saying Toyota wanted to come
to America to produce cars in America
because Congress was imposing tariffs on
foreign manufactured cars GM wanted to
learn how to build small cars because GM
all the American cars at the time were
very big gas guzzlers and they had not
worked out how to economically produce
the kind of small cars the Toyota was
producing so they set up this joint
in the early 80s and what they did is
which was really radical was they took
the same workforce and the union leader
Fremont assembly convinced Toyota to
rehire the same workforce we're just
kind of a nuts thing to do but they
rehired them and they sent them to
Toyota city in Nagoya in Japan and
trained them in the Toyota Production
system and then they all came back to
start at the new me plan and within a
few weeks they were producing cars which
were the same quality as the Toyota cars
produced in Japan they met they were
making Camrys and they were releasing
cars there were much better quality than
anything that GM was producing in
America at the time and what that showed
was it wasn't the people that were the
problem it was the system that was the
problem what did they do
I said except sponsoring them a great
trip to Japan right well that was one
element of it and another element was
the fact they'd just been fired so they
were kind of ready to do anything which
are both very important I think that
can't be discounted but I think the key
thing that's different about the Toyota
Production system is and on the podcast
they they kind of talked about it is
it's being teamwork it's that everyone
works together to achieve customer
outcomes that we want which is kind of
what we talked about earlier so they're
kind of the practice that everyone talks
about is being able to stop the line so
at the old GM plants what would happen
is the plants if you've got a car the
way it works is the car goes along the
production line and you have a certain
amount of time as a worker working on a
particular thing to do your part of the
process before the car moves out of your
area
somewhere else and if you can't for
example get the door bolted on within
the time you have sorry that cars now
going to someone else and so what would
happen is cars would roll off the line
with things done badly or not working
properly and they would get pulled off
the line at the end and put into kind of
a parking lot to be fixed later
that's not the way things work at Toyota
Toyota if you can't get your work done
in I know something like 2:30 lot of
time you can pull a cord call the end on
cord and that will light up a signal and
a manager will come and help you and the
idea of the managers
helping you is pretty radical for GM
people because that was that was it was
a very antagonistic relationship but at
Toyota the manager will come and help
you and if you're not done by the time
you have available in total you can pull
the cord again and it will stop the
whole production line and that was that
was crazy talk for the people at GM and
people don't realize how often the hand
on call gets produced you might I mean
you might think he gets stopped you know
a few times a day
the end on cord in a typical Toyota
factory gets stopped gets pulled
thousands of times a day you know that
people find liens above the line or I
need more helpless I need I need help
happens thousands of times a day and
there's another one probably only a few
times a day yeah I don't know I actually
how often the production line stops but
it definitely does stop that's no K
thing to do and that idea that everyone
is working together and then the most
important thing is it's the judoka
concept again the idea of building
quality in that that was totally
different and so John shook in a paper
I think first Sloan management review
says the the big thing that changed was
giving the workers the tools and the
skills and the training to do their jobs
and giving them the power to achieve the
the customer outcomes they wanted to
achieve and that those behavior changes
were really fundamental hmm so again you
know influenza continues integration
allowing engineers to choose their own
tools allowing engineers to push stuff
out to production allow and giving
engineers the the ability to affect
customer outcomes and the ability to
learn for customer outcomes and putting
them in contact with the customers and
giving them the tools to do their job
and then also telling them what the
business outcomes that we all want as a
company are and not telling them here
are the features we want to build but
instead telling them here's the business
outcomes you want to achieve and you
work out the features you want to build
that's the analogy yeah so let's switch
from the culture no let's talk a little
bit about the practice and from what
you're saying one of the most important
practice is to have everything in
version control yes why is that so
so having everything in
control is important because for a
couple of reasons firstly say you can do
system level automated tests say for
example it's much easier as I like to
say to bring down a web system by
changing a firewall setting than it is
by changing a code setting so we should
be testing those high-risk changes with
the same rigor that we test code changes
and things like software-defined
networking and going to make that even
easier in the future I think but we need
to test database schema changes all
those different kinds of changes so
unless that stuff's in version control
you can't automate the provisioning of
those kinds of things and and running
database changes in as part of the
automated test process the other reason
it's important is both those stability
metrics so he talks about how time to
restore service was an important metric
in the event of a disaster you need to
be able to restore service in a
predictable amount of time and the only
way you can do that is if you can
recreate the configuration of your
production systems from information
stored in version control so just from a
disaster recovery point of view it's
really important to be able to do that
everything apart from your data should
be in version control and so as is
almost always the case the same things
that help increase throughput are the
same things that improve stability so
having stuff in version control
contributes to both of those things
improves through / because it allows you
to provision testing environments much
more quickly it also improves stability
because it allows you to do deployments
and disaster recovery much more or more
quickly as well hmm so you gave a talk
shortly before this interview and you
said if you're doing branches you're not
doing continuous integration can you
explain that to the people who have not
been on the clock yeah this is still in
2014 probably the most controversial
thing I say is that each branch is
basically a bad idea and I kind of used
that as a slogan and the truth is more
nuanced than that the problem is not
feature branches
the problem is long-lived feature
branches and in particular the problem
is feature branches with a lot of
changes on them so I still I'm still
okay to do my spike branches and delete
all the code afterwards right
is not actually branching the problem is
merging the problem is when you merge if
there's only two developers it's fine
but as the number of developers
increases what you find is I say I'm
working on some codes on a feature
branch and I get towards the end of my
feature may be it's taken a few days and
I find some really nice refactoring that
will make the code a lot nicer so I add
that refactoring and then I pushed to
master now at that point you've been
working on another feature for maybe a
few days you pull my change which
includes my refactoring that's actually
going to be a bit of a pain for you to
merge that refactoring in potentially
especially if your architecture isn't
ideal and the pain of that increases
nonlinearly with a number of people on
the team so the more people you have on
the team the more painful that merging
becomes and the longer the length of the
branch the more painful it becomes and
it actually inhibits good practice like
refactoring because the moment I do a
refactoring and force everyone else on
the team to take it they've been working
for a few days on something else all of
those other people are going to have to
take that merge and it's gonna impact
all of them and then you're not gonna be
very popular right just just to clarify
it by merging you don't mean the
technical merge conflict was get because
was get merging has become so much
easier on a code level it has but
there's also semantic badges so text
merges is one thing but and yeah I
certainly experienced it I'm sure of you
and many of the listeners of experience
there where you had a code where you had
a change that merged perfectly fine but
it still broke something because what
changed was not a conflict between two
lines of code but a conflict between you
know one thing used to call one function
or one method and now it's calling
another method and I changed that method
so there was no conflict but the
behavior of the system changed and we
didn't catch that and if you're lucky
your compiler or your unit test catches
it well yeah your unit test will catch
it absolutely if you've done a good job
doing that but again that will only be
caught once those two changes that
conflict semantically are on the same
code base and that can't happen if we
just may
from master onto our feature branches it
only happens when the feature branches
immersion with each other I mean the
only way you get to production is when
all the feature branches emerged and
that is a combinatorial problem it's not
a linear problem all right so one part
of having everything in version control
is obviously configuration management
what is configuration management ah
that's a great question because it's
gonna be used by different people in
different ways
I think configuration management is just
working out how to turn the bits in
version control into working systems
yeah so and we are talking of tools like
puppet chef and the answer will borrow
yeah I mean there's a whole range of
them obviously I'm the chef guy so I'm
gonna say that works pretty well but
yeah there's a whole range of tools on
the market for taking bits in version
control and then turning them into
working systems and normally it's not
just gonna be a configuration management
tool there's gonna be a bunch of other
stuff you need to do to do things like
creating packages for your software and
you know obviously you have to
everything is in scope by including
networking storage configuration of
firewalls or application servers
absolutely everything everything you
need to reproduce working production
systems is in scope and so fact that's
becoming easier but it's certainly not a
sold problem yeah um recently there also
have been a movement from going from
configuration management to moving it
more to contain a visualization like you
would do was docker does it add
something to the table for continuous
delivery yeah I think this is gonna
pioneered by Netflix Netflix had this
idea that the unit of deployment and the
unit of packaging would be an ami so
they had this thing here my are the
virtualization things for Amazon right
yeah ami is an Amazon machine image so
what they would do for their deployment
pipeline in Netflix is create an ami and
that machine image would move along the
pipeline to production and
and so that would be the unit of
packaging and deployment and they have a
tool I think called as one called bakery
which produces that ami moves it along
the production line and and so I think
what you've seen tools like docker like
you mention is actually moving to that
as the unit of deployment and that has
profound impacts not just for the way
you manage the lifecycle in production
it also has profound implications for a
developer lifecycle I think you know
vagrant revolutionized the way we were
able to test our software by making it
possible to create production like
environments on developerworks stations
which was like docker it becomes
possible to take the same things and use
them all the way through the process
from developers all the way through to
production so yeah I think that that's
that is profound
you have to architect your systems with
that in mind so if you're not working on
a greenfield system it's going to be
very hard to try and retrofit that in
and also there's always going to be a
place for tools like chef for
configuration management tools because
it's not just about that it's about all
the supporting infrastructure as well so
there's a high level kind of
orchestration piece and also all the
stuff there's not just the container
that you have to wire together to get it
to work properly hmm we recently had an
episode about vagrant we will have
upcoming episodes on Amazon Web Services
as well as on docker
so you might stay tuned to the show to
learn more about these tools
think we pretty much covered what I
wanted to say is there anything you want
to say which I didn't ask for uh I think
the only other thing that I I have found
really interesting especially doing the
this stay of DevOps report was that we
were able to quantify culture so he
talked about culture earlier on in the
show the model we used to quantify
culture I was guided by this guy called
Ron westrom and he was a guy who's a
sociologist who was studying safety in
the context of health care and aviation
and he created this model that allowed
him to predict safety outcomes in these
companies and what was interesting was
that we used this in the state of DevOps
report to measure people's culture and
it predicts IT performance so the same
med the same model that predicts culture
also predicts innovation you know
stability in throughput so that was kind
of a big eye-opener for me and again the
state of Davos reports gonna be in the
show notes and you should download it
and check it out to find out what the
Western model is I was actually sent to
me by John Hall sport journalist Paul
who's now head of ops EDC it's basically
you know I'll email him and he'll just
reply back with a PDF of some paper he's
read recently that he really likes and
so I get a lot of stuff from from him in
that way and this is one of those things
that you would never have known about
he's studying for a master's in safety
and Lund University in Sweden and
talking to all these people in aviation
and so that's another thing that is a
big eye-opener for me is the extent to
which we can learn so much by
collaborating with people in different
industries and domains and these models
that have been used for years in other
domains actually have a really important
implication of a software development
maybe leading leading from that you
recently moved from sort box to chef how
will people be able to collaborate with
you what is what is your role as VP
there so at chef I can have an
internally focused role where I'm
helping to build an organization
moves faster scale so taking a lot of
the stuff that I'm talking about in my
forthcoming book lean enterprise where
that will be discussed with your course
or yes bunnies also we're gonna have
berry on the shades talking about linear
enterprise but that was a book that was
fundamentally designed to help people
address all the organizational cultural
architectural issues that prevent them
from doing continuous delivery so all
the things we talked about earlier where
company said oh that sounds great it
can't possibly work here because XYZ
well we address X Y Z in the Lean
Enterprise you know Finance governance
risk management project management
portfolio management all that is covered
in the book and so basically I'm taking
a lot of those ideas and in using them
to help chef's move faster scale okay
cool
how can people find out more about you
you're on Twitter yep so I'm Jess humble
at Twitter I have a website continuous
delivery comm you can go and check out
there
I'm J's that's jezik chef calm but yeah
Twitter or Twitter's and you don't
really the best way to get in touch with
me
all right let's makes the episode thanks
very much for your time I think it was
very interesting thank you very much for
having me thanks to you for listening to
this show you will find all the books
mentioned there links in the show notes
so thanks very much i'm johannes from su
video goodbye thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by I Triple E software magazine for
more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website @ SC - radioman to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on itunes mention a message us on
twitter at se radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under the Creative Commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]